<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Usury is injury Cleared in an examination of its best apologie, alleaged by a countrey minister, out of Doctor Ames, in his Cases of conscience, as a party and patron of that apologie. Both answered here, by Nath: Holmes, Dr. in Divinity.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1382:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Usury is injury Cleared in an examination of its best apologie, alleaged by a countrey minister, out of Doctor Ames, in his Cases of conscience, as a party and patron of that apologie. Both answered here, by Nath: Holmes, Dr. in Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Bishop, for Iasper Emery, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Eagle and Childe in S. Pauls Church-yard next Watlin street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Ames, William.  De conscientia et ejus jure vel casibus libri quinque.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Vsury is injury.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ames, William, 1576-1633. --  De conscientia et ejus jure vel casibus libri quinque.</term>
               <term>Usury --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4377:1"/>
            <p>USURY IS INJURY.</p>
            <p>Cleared in an examination of its beſt Apologie, alleaged by a countrey Miniſter, out of Doctor <hi>Ames,</hi> in his <hi>Caſes of Conſcience,</hi> as a party and Patron of that Apologie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both anſwered here,</hi> By NATH: HOLMES, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. in Divinity.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Richard Biſhop,</hi> for <hi>Iaſper Emery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Eagle and Childe in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard next <hi>Watlin</hi> ſtreet. 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:4377:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4377:2"/>
            <head>USURY IS INJURY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rother, our Conference <note n="a" place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c. <hi>28.</hi> An Dom. <hi>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> falling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Uſury, and that drawing in your mention of Doctor <hi>Ames,</hi> as if ſome Patron of it, or of ſome kinde of it, <hi>viz.</hi> 8 l' <hi>per centum,</hi> 8 l' in the hundred; upon my reading of the Doctor, at my retiring home, I could not but repeat him, and report my opinion of his paſſages <note n="b" place="margin">A week <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: So that my intent is not now to load this paper with an heap of weighty matter, that I could urge againſt Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, out of Scripture, and moſt ſorts of learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Heathens, Poets, Philoſophers, Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Moraliſts, Jewes, Rabbins, Targum, Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud, Chriſtians, Schoolmen, Lutherans, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts, &amp;c. but onely to walke over and view the limits of the queſtion, ſo farre as we have you and Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> in our company; whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4377:3"/> ſometimes I oppoſe; yet not I, but Scripture and reaſon; pardon me till you weigh my reaſons. He had not beene a man, if he could not have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ando<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue &amp; dormitat Homerus. Bernard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et omne.</hi> Seraphicall <hi>Bonaventure</hi> erred ſoulely in his Pſalter: Angelicall <hi>Aqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> by a miſtake, ſacrificed his wit in Purgatory: <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> though ſtiled Irrefragable, is ſometime not ſo tolera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in his defence of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: <hi>Ariſtotle, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lo who am maxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the Maxime of the Schooles, when at a loſſe in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning was forced many times (as learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deſcribes) to ſpeake ſo equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocally and amphibologically, as that he may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently be underſtood <hi>in utramque partem.</hi> Nor are the learnedſt Fathers without their <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi,</hi> as the learned <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath ſhewed in a briefe Synopſis: No; nor are our ſoundeſt moderne writers alwayes in the way. It is our miſery (and therefore <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cum jam cauſa jubet renovare dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) that the greateſt Linguiſts have ſtammered with their tongues. The Septuagint 70 times. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yriack oft in words. The Chaldee oft loſing the ſelfe. <hi>Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>Buxto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> and other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, inconſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in moſt and beſt copi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s uſually to be had, doe read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. We know (with all reverence be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Canone</hi>) that the Apoſtles could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erre in action,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſwerved ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uching ceremonies of the Jewes, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> might ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Jewiſh and Chriſtian with a kinde of diſſimulation, as Saint
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4377:3"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> cals it. Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> goes farther in his <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmino enervato, Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>De ſufficientia Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae. Neque enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>omnia que P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophetae aut Apoſtoli ſcripſerunt, ſunt ſtatim Canonica, ſed quae Deus in illum finem ſanctificavit.</hi> No wonder therefore if Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> or you, ſometimes miſſe your way. Therefore in all, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us all, ſeeing we are but men, <hi>divinam conſulamus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one another as we follow Chriſt. Now to the queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſura eſt lucrum ex mutuo quaeſitum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vi ipſius mutui.</hi> Uſury is a gaine ſought by lending, by force of that lending.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>An Vſura hujuſmodi ſit licita?</hi> Of this kinde of Uſury, the queſtion is, whether it be lawfull.</p>
            <p>Therefore for any learned man,<note place="margin">Replicatio</note> whoſe parts I otherwiſe admire, to diſtinguiſh of <hi>Vſura licita &amp; illicita,</hi> it is a meere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">A begging of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> queſtion</note>. He makes one member of the diſtinction to determine a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Uſury, when the queſtion is of Uſury in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, whether it be lawfull. <hi>Pace tanti viri,</hi> that in and upon the queſtion ſhall ſo diſtinguiſh, he commits a ſoloeciſme in diſputation, too great to be ſeeme ſo great a ſcholler. For evidently that Queſtioniſt of the lawfulneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Uſury is beaten with his owne diſtinction. For if he diſtinguiſh that there is <hi>Vſura licita,</hi> why makes he the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>An Vſura ſit li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ita,</hi> indefinitely. Therefore learned <hi>Ames</hi> never ſo diſtinguiſheth, but firſt defines, then queſtioneth, thirdly, ſtateth the queſtion.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4377:4"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vſura talis, qualis à daniſtis ac foeneratoribus vul. gò exercetur, ab omnibus meritò improbatur.</hi> Such Uſury as is commonly uſed by the lenders on inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and Uſurers, is juſtly diſallowed of all men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> Therefore you did ill to ſpend your breath in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Uſury, for their ſakes who are <hi>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtae ac foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratores,</hi> guilty <hi>talis Vſurae quae vulgò exercetur:</hi> Except in this, that its evident their Uſury is worſe than the commoneſt ſort; inſomuch that a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor was confident that it was extortion. If this exception were not, ſeeing our common Uſury is 8 l' <hi>per Cent.</hi> ſtrictly required by the Uſurer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Centum</hi> win or loſe, it fully comes within the compaſſe of Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> his utter diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and his ſentence that it ſhould be diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all <note n="c" place="margin">So far there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llowing 8 l' <hi>per Cent</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as affirmed in our di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>courſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion, the ſaid no more, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> followes out right in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>red.</note>. And if the Vſurer alleageth that he puts not the Vſe in the Bond; yet he doth in his bowelleſſe heart and bowels: that if it be not fully paid, he will ſuddenly take in his Principall, the Client being ſo unprovided, that Vſury in the beginning, ends in unmercifull ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orting cruelty. <hi>Summum jus ſumma injuria.</hi> ſo hang a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor condemned to die, without ſufficient allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time for preparation, may be the murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his ſoule. And this ſudden calling in of money, as in the cauſe, <hi>ſcil.</hi> mentall Vſury, is naught, ſo in the effect worſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to make men mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gage, or ruine their eſtate, to ſatisfie theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe Donivoros, theſe Anthropopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos, theſe man-eating Vſurers. Therefore this learned Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> bids us obſerve his defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4377:4"/> of Vſury; it is <hi>Lucrum ex mutuo qu eſitum, non conventum; quia non tantum Vſura realis in qua pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum intercedit, ſed &amp; mentalis, quae verſatur in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentione, lucrum ut debitum ex mutuo acquirendi, ista deſcriptione contineatur. i.</hi> Vſury is a gaine ſought by lending, not covenanted, becauſe not onely reall Vſury, which is by compact, but alſo mentall Vſury, which lies in the intention of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting gaine as a due by lending, is contained in that deſcription.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Generaliter tamen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; abſolutè illicitam eſſe quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet Vſuram, nulla ratione naturali ſolidè poteſt probari.</hi> But that generally all Vſury is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawfull, it cannot be proved by any naturall reaſon, ſolidly.</p>
            <p>We muſt remember how this learned Doctor lived where the people are intolerable Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers:<note place="margin">Replicatio</note> It had beene in vaine therefore in ſuch a place, <hi>è Cathedrâ,</hi> to have condemned all Vſury, and to have hoped to have ſitten faſt. And if the Doctor meane by naturall reaſon, reaſon from nature: 1. We have reaſon from nature, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by nature, I meane, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> meere animals, that have nothing but nature, meere heathens: whereby my conſcience is perſwaded, that it is a dictate of nature in ſome ſort, at leaſt an experiment obſerved by nature, that <hi>Vſura eſt illicita</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> minde is M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Cap<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vſury, at the end of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> The heathens have condemned this ſinne by the light of nature p 44<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Politicks, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. ſaith plainly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Petrus Ramus</hi> renders ſo home, as that it is evident he was of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:4377:5"/> minde; thus, <hi>Quapropter ejuſmodi nummorum foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (of money bringing forth money) <hi>naturae maxime, contraria atque inimica judicanda eſt.</hi> Therefore that kinde of Vſury of money produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing money, is to be judged as moſt contrary, and an enemy to nature. And 4. <hi>lib. Ethic. cap.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> That I may not ſeeme to wreſt the words in tranſlating <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus</hi> as an indifferent man ſhall render the Greeke for us;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alii</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus in accipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imit, quia undique, &amp; puia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ales ſunt it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui il i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ales o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as praeſtant, ſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue artes exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cent, &amp; lenones, &amp; omnes hujus notae homines, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ii quibus exigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um lucrum magna mercede conſtat. Hi omnes a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, &amp; quantum non delent, auferunt.</hi> The Philoſopher concludes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Communis autem eorum videtur eſſe lucri tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pitudo.</hi> O her; exceed in taking, <hi>viz</hi> any thing from any, <hi>viz.</hi> men of illiberall and ſordid arts, Bawds, &amp;c. Vſurers, &amp;c. all which receive of whom and how much they ought not, and ſordid gaine is common to them all. The Poet <hi>Horace, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Serm. Satyr.</hi> 2. condemns Vſury of 5 l' <hi>per cent.</hi> his words are, <hi>Dives agris, dives poſitis in foenore nummis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inas hic capiti mercedes e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſecat, i. e.</hi> five upon the principle: ſo learned Commentators: and a little before, <hi>Omnia conductis co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mens obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia nummis.</hi> i. Saith the Commentator, <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4377:5"/> foenori acceptis, pro quibus merces ſolvitur. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> a Heathen, condemns Vſury, <hi>Primum impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qu ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us qui in odia hominum incurrunt, ut po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum &amp; oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum. Cato</hi> a Heathen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes Vſury, ſaying it is <hi>idem a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> 2. I might thus in the ſecond place prove Vſury to be condemned by the Dictates of Nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe condemned of all mankinde, all peoples, Nations and Countries, more or leſſe. Of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens we have heard. Of Jewes after. For the lawes of Nations, ſuch as are the civill lawes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in all Kingdomes and Common-wealths, where men are not ſavage, firſt they deny a known Vſurer power to make a Will. Secondly, deny him right to be buried in Church or Church-yard. Thirdly, in Court they allow not Vſe for money detained when recovered. Againe, for Canon Lawes received of Chriſtians, Papiſts and Proteſtants, in ſome ſort: I meane Latine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, they injoyn tithes to Miniſters to be paid of all profits, and ſo Vſurers to pay the tenth of their Vſe; but Miniſters may not receive it, becauſe the gaine is all unlawfull and wicked and ſo the tithe. The Canoniſts and Canon Law doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all Vſury and intereſt whatſoever. So <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> on <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. Our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ute Lawes expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Vſury of 8 l' <hi>per Cent.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Conſcience. And in the judgement of Councellors <hi>his au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lus la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atute do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>not allow and approve of taking any Vſe, but onely provides a man ſhall not be puniſhed by the Common Law if he take but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l per Centum.</hi> The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4377:6"/> parent may omit correction of a younger childe for that vice which the parent doth not allow. Againe they ſay, the maine intent of the Statute is to hinder above 8. not to encourage to take 8 l' <hi>per Centum.</hi> Our Engliſh Canon, <hi>viz. Can.</hi> 109. is expreſſe that it is a great ſinne,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s et a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſe Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es &amp; I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ht<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> Auguſt. Epiſt. 54. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ret. cau. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 1</note> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentable. And our <hi>Epiſc. Trienn.</hi> viſit laſt held, expreſſed in articles that it was preſentable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. If D. <hi>Ames</hi> meanes by naturall reaſon, proper, and pertinent, and evident reaſon; ſure that reaſon that doth convince, is ſuch. And whether our reaſons will convince, we will leave to the Reader to judge in the premiſes and that which is to follow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Non probatur ratione eorum qui dicunt mutuum ex naturâ ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> debere eſſe gratuitum. Neque enim probari hoc poteſt, omne mutuum, quibuſcunque cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiis veſtiatur, debere eſſe gratuitum. i. e.</hi> It is not proved (that is Vſury to be unlawfull) by their reaſon that ſay Borrow of its owne nature ought to be <hi>gratis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatie.</note>
               <hi>Omne mere purum putum mutuum,</hi> and of that is the queſtion (whether conſideration be to be given for bare lending) is eaſily and evidently proved it ought to be <hi>gratis. Luk.</hi> 6.34, 35. <hi>If ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad to them of whom ye hope to receive, what thank have ye, for ſinners do ſo. But lead, hoping for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Capel</hi> times this a from place a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt Vſury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nor or can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Law againſt V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Moſes;</hi> for ſuch lawes as ſuch, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Moſes:</hi> but Heathens of all ſorts, and that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ature, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſin, having never heard of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apol treall la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Beſides we have it forbidden in the New <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ials <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35.</note> We explaine this in our proper
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4377:6"/> idiome of our tongue and common ſpeech, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that which is free in this kinde, borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lending: that which is not, we call by other names of contract, as letting and hiring. But the text is cleare enough, which forbids mentall expectation of gaine; calling lending for gain to be a doing as ſinners do. Vpon theſe words <hi>Beza</hi> having fetcht a circuit, concludes point blanck, thus; <hi>Illud tamen certum eſt, ſi juvandus eſt proximus, etiam nullà recipiendae ſortis habita ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> (but this I ſhould count rather giving than lending) <hi>multo magis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Beza) prohiberi foeneratorias pactiones. Gregorie Niſen</hi> on theſe words ſaith, <hi>Malignam foe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum excogitationem ſi quis appelles furtum, &amp; homicidium, non peccabit. Nam quid refert ſuffoſſo pariete quenquam erepta poſsidere acf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>norum neceſſitate poſsidere illicita. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame effect as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth in his Politicks, that it is unnaturall and unreaſonable that it ſhould be expected that mony ſhould bring forth money. The Papiſts in their Rhemes Teſt. ſhame us Proteſtants: The words are, It may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a pretext (as well as counſell) wherein V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, <hi>i. e.</hi> the expectation not of the mony lent, but of vantage for lone, is forbidden, as by other places of Scripture it is condemned. And it is a thing againſt the law of Nature and Nations. And great ſhame and pitty it is, that it ſhould be ſo much uſed and ſuffered among Chriſtians, or ſo covered and cloked under the habit of other contracts as it is. In a word, S. <hi>Matthew</hi> will clear it, that giving is not here ſpoken of; who <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.42. repeats our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4377:7"/> text of lending, and ſpeaks of giving beſide, as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct way of helping a neighbour. It were ſtrange therefore that S. <hi>Luke,</hi> that is the moſt eloquent writer of all the four Evangeliſts, ſhould confound giving &amp; lending to be all one; eſpecially againſt the nature of the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to lend,<note place="margin">May S. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p 6. ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to had ſpoken of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſpeake of lendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note> never to give; commonly to lend on Vſury, ſeldome ſignifying to lend otherwiſe; whence <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an Vſurer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Vſury. So <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Syriack ſignifying alwayes to lend, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to give; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifying an Vſurer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Amet.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Et ſi concedatur hoc (omne mutuum debet eſſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitum) nihil aliud inde ſequeretur, quàm mutuum ſi gratis non fiat, tranſire in alium contractum, vel no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel innominatum, vel ſimplicem, vel mixtum. i.e.</hi> And if it be granted that all lending ſhould be <hi>gratis,</hi> nothing would follow thence, but that then lending (if it be not <hi>gratis</hi>) would paſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another kinde of contract, named or unnamed, ſimple or mixt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>But this, <hi>Nihil aliud,</hi> is <hi>magnum aliquod quod inde ſequeretur.</hi> For by the ſame reaſon that the Doctor diſtinguiſheth that <hi>mutuum ſi gratis non fiat, tranſire in alium contractum, vel nominatum, vel innominatum, vel ſimplicem, vel mixtum;</hi> we may goe on, diſtinguiſhing, <hi>licitum vel illicitum, conductitium vel foeneratorium:</hi> For this will of neceſſity follow, that if a man lend wearable goods, that returne not in the ſame perfection every way as they were when lent, in conſideration whereof the lender takes reward: now lending
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4377:7"/> doth <hi>tranſire</hi> into hire. If he lends mony, that by number, weight and quality, returnes as good as it went out, yet for the bare loane requires re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, here lending doth <hi>tranſire</hi> into Vſury. And ſo the Doctor <hi>innominat,</hi> doth <hi>ſimpliciter</hi> grant the queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non probatur (viz. omnem Vſuram eſſe illicitam) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione eorum qui allegant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in rebus illis quae uſu conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muntur dominium non diſtingui ab uſu, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> adeo pro uſu nihil poſſe accipi ultra valorem ipſius dominii; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponnetur, enim lucrum accipi non ſimpliciter pro uſu rei mutuatae quoad ſubſtantiam, ſed quoad valorem aut proventum qui manet poſt ſubſtantiam conſumptam, &amp; ſubſiſtit ſaepe in rebus quae uſu non conſumuntur &amp; pro officio, vel actu mutuandi unde commodum perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit mutuarius.</hi> All Vſury to be unlawfull, is not proved by their argument that alleage that in thoſe things which weare with the Vſe, the rule or Maſterſhip of them is not diſtinguiſhable from the uſing of them, and therefore nothing above the value of that Maſterſhip can be taken for the Vſe: For it is anſwered, that gaine is not taken ſimply forthe Vſe of the thing borrowed, conſidered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſubſtance, but conſidered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the value or In-come which redounds after the ſubſtance is waſted, which oft-times conſiſts in things which are not impaired by their uſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is taken for the office and act of lending, from which the borrower receiveth profit.</p>
            <p>Of things waſtable by Vſe,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> there is not onely an impairing, but an hazard, and an event oft-times
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4377:8"/> of utter ruine. The hired horſe dies; And then he muſt paſſe only for the hire (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks) without farther ſatisfaction The hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red houſe not onely is worſe in the parts, every thing older and more rotted, but the principles and whole edifice fals, the tenant not bound, nor able to re-build. So that in taking hire there is not onely juſt ſatisfaction for wrong to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; But lawfull merchandize for hazard of the whole. But the Vſurer takes generally for the bare Vſe; For, for hazard he will run none. He uſually requires intolerable aſſurance, morgage, &amp;c. His money weares not. And for that ſame <hi>valor aut proventus qui manet poſt ſubſtantiam, &amp; ſubſiſtit ſaepe in rebus quae uſu non conſumuntur,</hi> of which the Doctor ſpeaks obſerve I pray you well: That, take away the conſideration of the ſubſtance of money (which the Vſurer hath <hi>in ſpecie &amp; nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> againe) and the act of lending, (which is ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by juſt repaying) and there is nothing to come into conſideration, no <hi>proventus</hi> the Vſurer is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of, which otherwiſe the Vſurer would or could make of his money, in conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſhould demand Vſe. For the Vſurer lends, having now no penurious need of Vſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelfe by: Being uſually rich, and alwayes richer than the juſt borrower; or however, he hath, or will have nothing elſe to doe with his money: But (as I know upon my owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) makes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lands, ſtock, &amp;c, to provide an Vſury banck. He is a lazie Caterpiller, and will not worke, and therefore turnes Vſurer. He is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4377:8"/> upheld by learned men that there is a lawfull Vſury (though nor he, nor they, can reherſe any marks the Scripture hath ſet down to diſtinguiſh them) and therefore he will not runne the hazard to be a partner with any body. He will not lend to be lent to againe, for he needs not borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If any man will borrow and doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe or intimate he will pay for the act of lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he will keepe his money a companion for canker and ruſt, rather than lend. If a man would bring home his money a month or two before the time, he is utterly unwilling, unleſſe the whole time be paid for. He will have it go on, and take for time, that was never his to ſell: yet he will have Vſe for all his money, for all the time he prayed, heard Sermons, received the Communion: For the time of eating ſleeping, &amp;c. when, nor he nor his client could or ought to be otherwiſe buſied. Let not the Reader now unjuſtly untwiſt this anſwer, but take all together, and let him ſpeak whether the Vſurer himſelfe can alleage that he receives his Vſe for any thing but lending. 2 If it were ſo as the Doctor ſpeaks, that <hi>poſt ſubſtantiam remanet valor &amp; proventus</hi> (which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found immediately in money) yet ſeeing God hath allowed recompence for uſing impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able goods, forbidden recompence for lending things that come in the ſame, <hi>quod &amp; quantum,</hi> the caſe is altered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non probatur (uſuram eſſe illicitam) ratione eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui objiciunt pecuniam ſua natura eſſe ſterilem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4377:9"/> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> Vſury is not proved unlawfull by the allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that ſay, that money in its owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is barren.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio</note>The father of the Philoſophers, <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as you heard afore, thought this a good reaſon, not onely to condemne Vſury, but to pronounce it contrary to nature. The fathers of Chriſtians, thinke the ſame. So <hi>Baſil</hi> on <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. as you heard afore. It is ſtrange that we having the eyes of the fathers to ſee with beſide our owne, ſhould not be able to ken as farre into the nature of <hi>vitium,</hi> as a meere heathen. ☞ <hi>Conſilio Lateranenſi,</hi> Vſury is thus defined; <hi>Quando ex uſu rei quae non germi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, nullo labore, nullo ſumptu, nullo periculo lucrum conquiri ſtudetur.</hi> To which <hi>Willet</hi> aſſents, and Engliſheth it in this manner; Vſury is when by the Vſe of a thing which increaſeth not, gaine is ſought without any labour, coſt, or hazard. You heard before alſo that the <hi>Rhemiſh Teſtament</hi> ſaith, It is againſt the law of nature. Finally, many learned men from this ſeeking money to be borne as it were of money, have conceived the word Vſury to be derived. <hi>Vſura, q.d. Vſus aeris.</hi> Not onely Divines touch this <hi>ſ.</hi> Tench, but Lawyers. I have read it in the Lord <hi>Cooks Reports</hi> in French. Hence alſo the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which firſt ſignifies <hi>partus,</hi> then Vſury. So Latine, <hi>Foenus, q.d. Foetus,</hi> the Etymologie riſing from a wonder.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Quamvis enim pecunia ſua natura &amp; per ſe ſit ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilis, facile tamen commutari poteſt in merces, quae
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4377:9"/> fructum edunt, &amp; accedeate induſtria utentis vim ſuam confert ad fructum pariendum.</hi> For though money in its owne nature is barren, yet it may eaſily be changed into commodities which fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, and by the induſtry of him that uſeth it, brings forth fruit.</p>
            <p n="1">1 This anſwer is not ſufficient,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> unleſſe it be a true univerſall propoſition, that for whatſoever worldly benefit that is barren in it ſelfe, yet eaſily commutable into profit, recompence may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>ſ.</hi> for the forbearance of it. For if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition be but particular or ſingular; then we want other proofes to cleare why it ſhould be true of money, more than other things. But the propoſition is not univerſally true. For then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe time, unprofitable in it ſelfe, being not <hi>res,</hi> but <hi>menſura rerum,</hi> is profitable by induſtry, <hi>Accedente induſtria utentis,</hi> therefore it may be ſold. As indeed uſurious and injurious merchants ſell their commoditie, not according to the rate, but according to the value of time, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the learned, that condemne Vſury. Then the Elements, Fire and Water, <hi>bona commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and therefore <hi>gratis</hi> to be communicated to one another (ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi>) might be let out or ſold for money, becauſe mediately they are very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. One neighbour might ſell them to another wanting them: or the Magiſtrate lay a tax upon men for the uſe of them. 2 Money brings not forth profit, by all induſtry of all men, but by ſingular induſtry of ſome, and with ſome hazard.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4377:10"/> Moſt men are not rich, moſt men not gaining by money, but many, many times looſing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one argument of Polititians againſt Vſury is, it is unlawfull, and againſt nature, becauſe the Vſurer by Bonds, Bils, Suits, &amp;c. requires of his Client <hi>quod non eſt in rerum natura;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of money where none was, but loſſe <note n="k" place="margin">No man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols <hi>Midas</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the more, that his fingers could turne bread into gold, as long as he loſt in bread what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t in gold. Nor is the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers money to be admired, if it could be tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>read: ſeeing what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on in bread, is loſt in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of ſoule. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r without in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bread, &amp;c. 1. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>das</hi> bread was not turned into gold without a moſt fooliſh wiſh.</note>. 3 The Maxime applied to particulars, pincheth; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vſury money, <hi>i. e.</hi> money lent on Vſury be fruitfull mediately, <hi>&amp; per accidens.</hi> The Text, <hi>Prov</hi> 28.8. may juſtly make us doubt. If God curſe not, croſſe not borrower or lender (for it is ſeldome ſeene but the borrower is ſwallowed whole at laſt) yet if the borrower upon Vſe, ſels unconſcionably dear, that he may make his cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to pay for the commodity, pay his Vſe, and finde him preſent maintenance, and an eſtate for time to come, what boaſt can there be made of the fruitfulneſſe of this money to the Common-wealth? The Country is ſacrificed on cruell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſave one man. The Common-wealth muſt periſh for the wealth of ſuch Commons. 4 The rule of the husbandman in buying of Cattell and other commodities, or Leaſes, is, that he will pay for what the thing is <hi>in ſtatu praeſenti:</hi> but to pay for what it is improveable to, he hath no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. If money be fruifull that is borrowed of the Vſurer, yet ſeldome ſo fruitfull as honeſtly to pay the Vſer for his great paines, and the Vſurer his Vſe too.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Non probatur (illicitam eſſe uſuram) ratione eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4377:10"/> qui dicunt in genere nihil eſſe in mutuo, pro quo lucrum poſsit accipi. Eſt enim proventus fructus qui ex pecuniâ mutuo datâ poteſt expectari: eſt &amp; onus annexum privationi pecuniae qua fit ut omnis occaſio eandem cum fructu alias collocandi omittatur. Vacatio enim à pecunia utendâ eorum jure aeſtimari poſſe videtur, quo &amp; vacatio à laboribus aeſtimatur. Exod.</hi> 21.19. <hi>i.e.</hi> Uſury is not proved unlawfull by their reaſon, who ſay, that in generall there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in lending for which gaine may be taken. For there is both a fruitfull in come to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of lent money; as alſo there is a burthenſome inconvenience annexed to the want of that lent money, whereby all opportunity of diſpoſing that money otherwiſe, is taken away: For non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployment of money that may be uſed, ſeemes valuable, with the ſame equity valuable, as non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployment of labour, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.19.</p>
            <p>I have ſufficiently anſwered all theſe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> onely to the laſt reaſon or clauſe <hi>[Vacatio etenim, &amp;c.]</hi> I will ſpeak a word. As now it is the queſtion whether Uſury be lawfull (as out of doubt labour in our Callings is) and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether Gods bleſſing may be expected on ſuch money-mungring. So (which is the maine of our anſwer) the husbandman is ſure (under Gods ordinary providence) what he can get by his daily labour, day by day: but at abundance of hazards that he doth not loſe by his laying out of his money (eſpecially his Vſury-borrowed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) as much in one day as he can get in many
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4377:11"/> weeks. Therefore there is not <hi>par ratio,</hi> that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of mony ſhould be recompenced (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when men deſired to lend their mony for ſo long time, ſix moneths, &amp;c. as confident it would be no hinderance to them) as bodily labour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Ratione evidenti confirmatur, aliquam uſuram eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe licitam; quia nulla realis differentia poteſt oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, inter quandam Vſuram, &amp; alios contractus ab omnibus probatos. e. g. Eſt aliquis pecuniâ inſtructus ad praedium emendum, unde poſsit percipere annuos fructus centum imperialium. Idem praedium cupit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter habere, ſed non est pecuniâ inſtructus. Si prior ille emat praedium, &amp; elocet alteri pro centum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialibus, quin juſtum &amp; aequum fecerit, nemo nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. Si vero alteri det pecuniam ad idem praeſtandum, ſc. ad idem praedium ſibi emendum, &amp; candem ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ab eo accipiat, eidem periculo ſeſe ſubjiciens, cui in exemptione ſua fuiſſet obnoxius, eadem pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt juſtitia. Et praeterea nonnihil accedit alteri illi qui ſelvit uſuras ratione dominii in praedium il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud quod emptione ſu acquiſivit: i.e.</hi> It is ratified by evident reaſon, that ſome Vſury is lawfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there cannot be ſhewed any reall difference betweene a certaine kinde of Vſury, and other contracts approved of all. For inſtance, there is a man furniſhed with money to buy ſuch a Farme of an hundred pounds <hi>per annum:</hi> Another man, though wanting money, deſired to buy the ſame Farme: If the firſt of theſe buy the Farme, no doubt but he may lawfully let it out to another for an hundred pounds by the yeare. Now if this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4377:11"/> man now the owner, ſhould not have bought it, but have lent his money to the other, that want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money deſired to buy it, wherewith he now buyes the Farme, taking of this purchaſer the ſame ſumme of rent for his money, which he ſhould have had of the Farme, putting himſelfe upon the ſame hazard for his money to which he ſhould have beene liable in the purchaſe of the Farme, there is the ſelfe ſame equity in both.</p>
            <p>Vpon this argument and caſe I ſuppoſe was the ſpeech at our conference grounded (for I finde none ſo like as this) that D. <hi>Ames</hi> allowed 8 l'. in the hundred.<note place="margin">Repicatio</note> But there was an utter miſtake in this, as will appeare eaſily to him that reads the bare words. It will further appeare by our anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Here the Doctor plainly allowes a man to take ſo much in the hundred for his money, which he lends to a purchaſer of Free-land, or Farme, as the purchaſe bought brings in of yearely rent, if it were let. Which is in <hi>England</hi> (and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it to be ſo in other Countries; for Vſury, too too common in all lands in the practiſe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes that proportion of purchaſing) I ſay is in <hi>England</hi> but 5 l' in the hundred, which is farre from 8 l' in the hundred. 2 The phraſe <hi>eidem pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculo ſeſe ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jiciens,</hi> carries very much with it. Which the learned Doctor not ſo verſed in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing, as he was in peruſing of books, might not ſo well conſider. For firſt if by it he means ſimply, that a man in lending out his money to buy <hi>Centum imperialia per annum,</hi> doth run him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4377:12"/> into the ſame hazard in lending his money, as he ſhould have done in purchaſing, if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had laid out the money on the purchaſe: And that therefore he ought to have as much for the lone of the money, as he ſhould have had of rent, if the purchaſe had beene his, which rent his client or borrower now takes up of the Farme as rent, and payes it him as Vſe: the worthy Doctor is much miſtaken. 1 What great hazard there is in purchaſing (over there is in lending money, for which men are faine to give double, treble, quadruble bond, with morgages, ſtatutes, pawnes, &amp;c. for ſecurity, even what the Vſurer will require) I ſay hazard in purchaſing, in regard of conveyance, leſt ſome morgages or ſtatutes ſecretly lie on the land, or ſome former eſtate be let, or the new leaſe be not well made, ſome <hi>the</hi> for <hi>a,</hi> or <hi>and</hi> for <hi>but,</hi> marring all: Or ſome Entailes, or Thirds, &amp;c. worſt the bargaine, with hundreds more difficulties, I leave to the Lawyer to declare. 2 What great charges for fines, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, conveyances, with many journies to ſettle a purchaſe, over there is to lend money to Vſe, which coſts the Vſury-taker nothing, I leave the purchaſer to diſcourſe. 3 How uncertaine the rates of commodities be, how wearable the ground is, how alterable by ſeaſons of exceſſe of wet or drought the crops are, and conſequently how prices of land fall, eſpecially in any trouble of common-wealths, of wars, &amp;c. whiles money is ſtill of the ſame value, let the husbandman ſpeake. 4 How much labour and coſt a man is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4377:12"/> at to make the Farme yeeld his rent, let the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupier or imployer of that Farme ſpeak, whiles the Vſurer is at none for the money he lends: and therefore it is a hard pennyworth for the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, if he imploy his Farme, to pay the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and be paid his labour and his charges too, ſo as to have a maintenance. Seeing therefore in no degree doth this lender run hazard and charges as the purchaſer, he is in no wiſe to have the ſame profit of his money as the purchaſer of his lands.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If we may ſo take the Doctor, as that he meanes the lender of his money ſhould alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>ſubjicere ſeſe eidem periculo cui in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptione ſua fuiſſet obnoxius;</hi> then it is as plaine as if written with a Sun-beame, as evident as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent may be, that now this is not Vſury, but partnerſhip, copurchaſing, coheirſhip, or joint-taking. And ſo all that this poſition hath ſet downe, gives no allowance to Vſury.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scriptura non tollit omnem omnino Vſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> The Scripture doth not altogether take away all Vſury.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Anſw.</hi> Moſt learned men (and ſome of them moſt pious) drawing out of the Scripture the ſelfe ſame definition of Vſury in effect,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> which Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> ſets downe, under that their defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion condemnes all Vſury, comming within the compaſſe thereof — <hi>Vrſinus, Vſura est lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum quod accipitur ſolius mutuationis cauſa — Calv. Quicquid lucri praeter ſortem dabatur, eſt uſura, unde Haebraicè dicta</hi> Tarbit: <hi>i. e</hi> Increaſe of the multiplying — <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si plus quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4377:13"/> expectas accipere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>C.</hi> 14. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>foenerator es — Cajetan</hi> a Papiſt, <hi>Plus ex mutuo velle quam mutuatum ſit, ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum eſt — Concil. Carthag.</hi> 3. <hi>Nullus Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum amplius accipiat quam cuiquam accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit</hi> — 2 The Scripture takes away all Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and it will be made to appeare even out of thoſe arguments that the worthy Doctor allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the contrary, which are foure. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Sed illam quae exigitur ab egeno, qui ob inſtantem, neceſsitatem &amp; ſuſtentationem ſuam aliquid mutuo petit: ita ut prohibitio fundetur in conditione perſonae. Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35, 36. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.17. <hi>e. i.</hi> But onely that which is exacted of the needy, who for his preſent urgent neceſſity, and the ſuſtentation of himſelfe, borroweth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what: ſo that the prohibition is grounded upon the condition of the perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio</note>We thus retort the argument. That ſin which is forbidden to all that are incident and ſubject to commit that ſin, is altogether forbidden, that it be not committed. But Uſury is forbidden to all that are incident &amp; ſubject to commit Vſury; <hi>Ergo.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> propoſition is evident thus; The takers of Uſury are the richer: The bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers are the poorer. And therefore the Lord forbids all rich men to take Uſe of their Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, becauſe they are poore in compariſon of the lender; and ſo have more need to have the Uſe money given them, than the rich borrower to receive it. <note n="l" place="margin">That the Vſurer is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man; &amp; others in oppoſition to him are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: we have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible place of Scripture, <hi>Pro.</hi> 22 2. The rich and the poore meet together. See poore put in oppoſition to this rich man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the onely rich man. Who is he? The Vſurer. See <hi>Prov,</hi> 29 13. comp. the margent.</note> For though a man of an 100 <hi>l</hi>'
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4377:13"/> 
               <hi>per annum,</hi> borrow of a man that hath but 50 l' <hi>per annum;</hi> yet he that hath the more lands and leſſe money, and more in debt, perhaps as much as halfe, or all his lands are worth, muſt needs be the poorer man. If any rich man borrow for wantonneſſe, and ſuperfluous and unneceſſary uſes; that's the ſpeciall ſin of borrowing &amp; borrowers: forbidden under another head, <hi>ſc.</hi> covetouſneſſe: And by other kinde of places of Scripture: <hi>Owe nothing to any one but love.</hi> So a man may abuſe a godly duty, <hi>viz. pr.</hi> to ſeeke things to get them, to conſume them on luſts, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 4 3.</note> Therefore in theſe places of Uſury, the holy Ghoſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together intent againſt the ſinne of lenders. And that is Uſury: whoſe aggravation is this in the Texts above named (as in other Texts other ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations of that ſinne are touched) that it takes gaine for lending, of them that are poorer than the lenders. Unleſſe this anſwer be admitted as ſound, it would follow by the ſame argument that the learned Doctor makes; That oppreſſion is not uviverſally forbidden, becauſe the mighty and potent ones uſually are forbidden that ſinne, toward the weake innocent neighbour, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes is weaker than the oppreſſor, elſe he would not be oppreſſed. No more would the poore borrower borrow if he were rich, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would be ready to lend, freely, or for Uſury. <note n="m" place="margin">To the ſame M. <hi>Elton</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers. If this conſequence were good, then becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.22. Rob not the poore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is poore. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man may rob the rich, becauſe he is rich. And <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. No mention is made of the poore, but V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den towards a brother, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore or rich.</note> Finally, that I may not ſeeme to goe an uncouth and untroden path, let the Reader looke on my company. 1 Maſter <hi>Capel</hi> in his Tract of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, hath upon this objection of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4377:14"/> theſe words in the forenamed booke, in his diſpute of reſtitution, at the end of the ſaid book. Read, and read his anſwer: <q>The Law (ſaith the objection) doth urge moſt, that Uſury be not done to the poore: Was it not (ſaith Maſter <hi>Capel</hi>) becauſe the Jewes were then too noble and generous to go a borrowing, except it were the poorer ſort? What ſhould the Law then forbid that to be done by rich men, which moſt rich men never did? But after we have probiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons plenty that are indefinite: we are forbidden we muſt not rob the poore, becauſe he is poore. Good ſport for theeves, if therefore it may be thought to follow, that it is a lawfull matter to rob the rich<note n="n" place="margin">The Scripture forbids taking Vſe of a poore brother a Iew, this is no tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be done to any Iew, for (ſaith Maſter <hi>Capel</hi>) there is no one place gives leave to hire his mony out to a rich Iewiſh f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note>. Neither can the law againſt Uſury be thought to be a judicious law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> for ſuch lawes as ſuch, are knowne onely by ſome intelligence from the books of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But heathens of all ſorts, who never once heard of <hi>Moſes</hi> writings, have with one voice cryed ſin upon Uſury, and ſhame upon Uſurers; Poets, Orators, Hiſtorians, Philoſophers, all.</q> Thus farre Maſter <hi>Capel,</hi> yet alive to maintaine his words againſt any. We will ſhew you but one or two more of our company, and leave the Reader to ſearch the multitude of ordinary authours.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Next followeth Maſter <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> on that place <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. quoted by Doctor <hi>Ames. Ainſworths</hi> words are, Uſury conſumeth a man and his ſubſtance; and is therefore here, and elſewhere abſolutely (marke it well, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely) forbidden, <hi>viz. Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35, 36.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4377:14"/> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.8. Obſerve, Maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> quotes the ſame places for abſolute forbidding Uſury, which Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> notes for forbidding onely to the poore. And he quotes beſide <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. where Uſury is forbidden to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards any Jew whatſoever. ☜ Maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> goes on, and learnedly produceth the ſtreames of Jewiſh Doctors and Rabbins to be againſt all Uſury, Uſury of any increaſe, Uſury of victuals, cloths, labour: Uſury of words and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations: Uſury of teaching one to read, for lending money. All Sureties, Scribes, Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, are forbidden to have to doe in Vſury. The Vſurer, ſay the Rabbins, offends againſt ſix pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions, <hi>viz. Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.37. of money. And againe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.37. of victuall. Againe, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36. of increaſe. Againe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. ſhall not lay upon him Vſury. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. and <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.14. For the Rabbins ſay, it is a laying a ſtumbling blocke before the blinde, to take Vſe. It is unlawfull to take Vſury before or after, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſend a gift before to him of whom one intends to borrow. Thus farre M. <hi>Ainſworth</hi> and his Rabbins, with much more; to make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians bluſh at once moving a tongue for Vſury.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Vatablus</hi> on this <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. hath theſe words, <hi>Pauperi per expoſitionem poſitum. Exponit enim quem vocet populum ſuum, nempe pauperes:</hi> Thus <hi>Vatablus.</hi> And let me here put in mine oare, thus; That if this were a limitation of Vſury, to take onely Vſury of the poore Jew, then it would follow one might take it of a rich Jew,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4377:15"/> which is no where allowed: And croſſeth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther limitation alleaged by D. <hi>Ames,</hi> out of the text of Scripture, that allowes Vſury to be done to none but to the ſtranger the <hi>Canaanite.</hi> And ſo theſe limitations fight one againſt another: But being made aggravations, they agree.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Vpon this, <hi>Exod</hi> 22.25. Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> (having before named ſeven kinds of Vſury) hath this aſſertion, That Vſury is ſimply unlawfull. He hath this explanation. But all theſe kinds of V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury and intereſt, with the like, were utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, and not to be practiſed among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. He hath finally this probation. The ſaid aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions and explanation ſhall appeare by theſe reaſons (whereof I will defer ſome of them till after, for a fitter place.) 1 Vſury (ſaith he) was deteſtable among the Heathen; much more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ought it to be among Chriſtians. As <hi>Cato</hi> being asked what it was to play the Vſurer, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Idem quod occidere.</hi> And further he ſaid, that in former time they uſed to puniſh a thiefe but in twofold, an Vſurer in fourefold <hi>Willet</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth for this his argument <hi>Calvin.</hi> 2 Vſury is againſt the firſt inſtitution of money. <hi>Pecunia inventa eſt,</hi> that thereby things neceſſary for the maintenance of this life might be provided. But now it is prevented and abuſed to covetouſneſſe, that money may increaſe money. Maſter <hi>Willet</hi> alleageth this his argument out of one <hi>Borrh.</hi> 3 The Scripture abſolutely condemneth Vſury, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.17. Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> may well ſay abſolutely, for here are no limitations
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4377:15"/> mentioned, which Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> ſets downe. Well, Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> goes on. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith he) ſignifieth increaſe. By which, ſaith he, all increaſe by Vſury is forbidden. Let me give you to underſtand here, whence this word <hi>Tarbith</hi> comes, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Arabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ltipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>catus eſt,</hi> up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n which word <hi>Tarinth, Schindler,</hi> one of the greateſt lingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts in fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Eaſtern tongues, <hi>Hebr. Cha'd S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>almudie. &amp; Arab.</hi> ſaith that <hi>Pro</hi> 28.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſura <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, viz. ſubſtant am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>preſſa, viz. uſura.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>☞Yet this is one of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> urged, that Vſury is here forbidden with a limitation, <hi>ſc.</hi> to the poore. When <hi>Schindler</hi> ſheweth that hence is fetcht the etymologie of Vſury, what it is, <hi>ſc.</hi> all increaſe for bare lending. And as our learned Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have rendred <hi>Tharbith,</hi> the caſe goes farre worſe againſt the Vſurer; for they rende <hi>Tarbith,</hi> unjuſt gaine. So that if one asketh what is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vſury. It is ſaith <hi>Schindler, Tarbit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> what is <hi>Tarbit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>?</hi> It is unjuſt gaine, ſay our Engliſh new Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; Therefore I conclude Vſury is unjuſt gaine.</p>
               </note>. 4 His next reaſon is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Chryſoſtome. Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith (quoth <hi>Willet) Vſurarius ſuper omnes mercatores maledictus.</hi> Curſed above all merchants and tradeſmen: So <hi>Willet</hi> tranſlates. And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (ſaith <hi>Willet</hi>) further uſeth this compariſon; Like as when one fifteth any graine, all the graine by little and little ſlippeth through, and ſo <hi>ſolum ſtercus remanet in cribro;</hi> onely the ſoile and dirt remaineth in the ſieve: So of all the ſubſtance and ill gotten goods of Vſurers, <hi>Nihil remanet niſi peccatum.</hi> So farre <hi>Willet.</hi> Thus you ſee the prohibition of Vſury in the above alleaged places by Doctor <hi>Ames, Non fundetur in conditione perſonae,</hi> not onely in my judgement and my reaſons (which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding are unanſwerable) but in the judgement of other learned men, with their invincible reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scriptura non tollit omnem omnino uſuram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fed il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam quae mordet aut rodit, i.e. quando debitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exigitur cum rigore, &amp; proximi damno. i.e.</hi> The Scripture takes not away all Vſury utterly, but the biting
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4377:16"/> and gnawing; <hi>i.e.</hi> when the debt is exacted with rigour, and damnifying our neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>To the firſt clauſe. 1 Thus as our Engliſh Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, <hi>O.</hi> or <hi>N.</hi> take no notice of the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Nor French, <hi>Iun. Lat.</hi> High-dutch; ſo here is not a limitation of Vſury, as if <hi>Neſhech,</hi> biting Vſury were unlawfull onely. As if there were another Vſury, which our old Vſurers call toothleſſe Vſury. For there is no Vſury ſo old, as that the marke is out of its mouth, but ſtill it may be knowne to be a ſinne. Still its teeth may be ſeene, and ſo called biting Vſury. This word is oft uſed as an epithite of aggravation, to deterre men from any Vſury. Becauſe any Vſury at the beſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Neſhech,</hi> A biting Vſury. For if we looke after the other names of Vſury, they have a worſe ſignification than this. 1 For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Neſhech,</hi> it is agreed that is condemned. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> cals it on <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Morſum aſpidis venena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> And that you may know what is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech,</hi> your friend (as the Vſurers report, if any will beleeve them) Maſter <hi>Zanch.</hi> will ſhew. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech, Morſus eſt, quo ſcilcet mordetur, id eſt, damno afficitur ille, qui mutuam accepit pecuniam, dum ſc. v. g. pro centum cogitur reddere centum, &amp; prater hos aliquid amplius, ſive parum, ſive multum.</hi> By which deſcription of <hi>Neſhech,</hi> all our Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers hundreds for one are caſt, and condemned guilty of biting Vſury. For they will have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more than the principle, let the borrower get nothing at all, but loſe. The Vſurer muſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4377:16"/> have a <hi>plus ultra,</hi> on his five in the hundred. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other his ſix in the hundred. Another his ſeven in the hundred. Another his eight in the hundred. Another his five ſhillings a moneth, or fifteene pence a weeke for two yeares, for five pounds; which in the <hi>pecunia numerata,</hi> by Lunary months, twelve in a yeare, comes to 20 l' <hi>per Centum:</hi> By Solary months, as the Sunne meaſures ſeven dayes to a weeke, foure weeks to a month, and ſo makes thirteene months in a yeare, it comes to thirty in the hundred. And <hi>in modo numerandi,</hi> the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of paying, that as ſoone as the ſtocke is out, to have ſome comming in within a weeke or a month, and ſo weekly or monthly, comes to above 30 l' in the hundred. For the 30 l' <hi>per Centum,</hi> you may reckon it thus; five ſhillings a moneth, for a yeare, for 5 l', comes to make the ſumme of 3 l', ſuppoſing but the Almanack Lunary moneths, 12 in the yeare. For 12 crowns are 3 l'. of which 3 l', 10 s is the Vſe. For the ſum was 5 l' for two years. Now halfe is come in at 12 Almanacke months. Now multiply; ten a yeare for 50 s, is twenty ſhillings for 5 l'. Then foure twenties, <hi>ſc.</hi> 4 l' for foure 5 l, <hi>i e.</hi> for 20 l': that is five 4 l' (which is 20 l') for five 20 l', which is an 100 l'. So you ſee then that ten ſhillings a yeare for 50 s, is 20 l' for an hundred. Lets goe on then; if ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a yeare, for 50 s, comes to 20 l' <hi>per Centum,</hi> then adde halfe ten ſhillings, <hi>ſc.</hi> five, for the odde Solary moneth, the thirteenth moneth in the yeare, and that will come to halfe as much more, <hi>i. e.</hi> 30 l' <hi>pro Centum.</hi> Theſe things I have recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4377:17"/> if I forget not my ſelfe, before exact Shop-keepers, Civill Lawyers, Common Lawyers, and Divines, and they have aſſented to the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be right. And the Lawyer hath pronounced directly this to be indirect Vſury (though a man pretend to ſell his money) and ſo lies liable to the penalty of the Statute. But then how much more than 30 in the 100 it comes to, to take in ſome of the Principall and Vſe together, the firſt week, or firſt month, and ſo weekly or monthly, for two years, till all in, I muſt confeſſe I cannot tell; I nevet yet tryed to reckon: and it ſeemes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what intricate: we had need have the helpe of the Almanack-maker. Others, may be, ſaile low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and take but 20 s in the hundred; yet if the borrower hath not gained thus much, this is <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech</hi> with Maſter <hi>Zanchie.</hi> Nay, if a man doth not leave the borrower ſome gaine, if he gat but one ſhilling, ſo that <hi>Creditor fit tamen particeps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitatis,</hi> of the gaine. that is <hi>Neſhech.</hi> We adde the judgment and reaſons of other learned men, that are contrary to D. <hi>Ames;</hi> that <hi>Neſhech</hi> doth not intend only to forbid one kinde of Vſury, but is a common name to diſgrace, and forbids all Vſury, as all Uſury being <hi>Neſhech,</hi> biting. It is <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> argument, &amp; he hath it out of learned <hi>Cajetan, Vſura eſt ex ſuo genere nociva,</hi> becauſe it is called <hi>Neſhech.</hi> And the law of nature, ſaith <hi>Willet,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth we ſhould not do as we would not be done by. It is <hi>Ainſworths</hi> poſition, <hi>Evod.</hi> 22.25. That Vſury is called biting, becauſe indefinitely all Vſury is biting, and therefore here ſaith he, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4377:17"/> forbidden. He hath this poſition as out of many Scriptures there quoted, of which afore: So out of the <hi>Heb. Rab. viz. Maimonid.</hi> Vſury indefinitely called <hi>Neſhech</hi> or <hi>Noſhech,</hi> it nippeth and eateth his neighbours fleſh. — <hi>Iun.</hi> out of <hi>Bernard, Vſura</hi> is called <hi>Neſhech, lucrum rodens, ſeu exedens;</hi> for it is, ſaith <hi>Bernard, Venenum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonii. — Willet</hi> out of <hi>R. Sol.</hi> and <hi>Lyran.</hi> Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is <hi>Neſhech, q. mordet ut ſerpens; parum percipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in principio, tandem devorat totam hominis ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam.</hi> Out of <hi>Galaſſ. q. tanquam hirudo, omnem ſuccum &amp; ſanguinem exſugit,</hi> as an horſleech, ſaith <hi>Willet.</hi> — Out of <hi>Simler, q. ut morſus ſerpentis non ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit dormire.</hi>—Out of <hi>Calvin, Neſhech quia foenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor tanquam canis famelicus, alios mordendo ſeipſum paſcit.</hi> — Finally, <hi>q. lethaliter mordet eos, qui eâ gravantur. ex Anonymo. Elton</hi> is of the ſame minde. All Vſury is <hi>Neſhech.</hi> You ſee then how bad Vſury is at beſt. How <hi>Neſhech</hi> is enough to condemne all Vſury almoſt. The next words are worſe. For <hi>Tharebith,</hi> in the words and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Maſter <hi>Zanchie,</hi> is of <hi>Rabbah. Quod eſt creſcore, i.e. augere. Vocem hanc habemus, Levit.</hi> 25. <hi>Significatur autem hac voce, uſura ſeſe multiplicans,</hi> (for indeed it is a Nowne from the Conjugation <hi>Hithpael.) Cum ſcilicet Vſura, (nempe iniqua) non perſoluta, novam parit Vſuram. Quam certè damnat Lex Dei, Levit.</hi> 25.36. <hi>Vbi utramque vocem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungit Neſhech &amp; Tharebith, &amp; utramque damnat, cavetque ne fiat. Quare neque haec vox in ſacris li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris in bonam partem accipi poteſt. Atque illam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Vſuram, quae Neſhech dicitur, vocant Iuriſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4377:18"/> noſtri Vſuram ſimplicem; alteram, uſuram uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum; cumſc. Vſura non exacta, parit novam Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram; &amp; Graeci vocant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quaſi dicat repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titam Vſuram.</hi> So then this <hi>Tharebith</hi> is not the toothleſſe or tolerable Vſury, but worſe than <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech,</hi> and therefore condemned by Scripture with <hi>Neſhech,</hi> in the ſame text. Yea, condemned by <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie,</hi> yea, as he explains it, by humane laws as moſt odious. <note n="p" place="margin">Pray marke now, that this piece of <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35, 36. is one of thoſe places which Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> produceth that Vſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, with this limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> to the poore. When a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you heare that the two words there to expreſſe Vſury, ſignifying ſuch a Vſury as for the nature is unlawfull to be done to any man whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, poore or rich. And it is not my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, but <hi>Zanchies,</hi> that ſeemes to be a favourer to Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. And <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech</hi> there u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> himſelfe, and therefore he ſomewhat ſmiteth himſelfe to ſay Vſury is forbidden, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36. to poore, becauſe poore. When it is rather forbidden, becauſe <hi>Neſhech:</hi> and ſoone makes any Client ſo poore new as to borrow, a non to be very poore.</note> Me thinks, <hi>Zanchie</hi> or <hi>Ames,</hi> or any man that would intimate a tolerable Vſury, ſhould have done ſo much as told us by what name that tolerable lawfull Vſury is called in old Teſtament, where they pretend it is allowed. But they leave us to our ſelves. Well therefore I goe on. The third word for Vſury is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <hi>Fraudes, Doli, Vſurae:</hi> It ſignifies cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cozening as well as Vſury, intimating that Vſury is of an odious abominable nature, to be ſhunned as a dangerous thing to intrap ones eſtate and livelihood. You ſhall not take my word for this, or learned <hi>Shindlers;</hi> but I will produce our Engliſh Bibles, and the beſt and laſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.13. it is ſaid, <hi>The poore and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull man meet together.</hi> The Hebrew word for deceitfull man is <hi>Iſh Terakim,</hi> the word before named. The man of cunning deceits; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſignifies the Vſurer, therefore in the margent it is rendred Vſurer. Beſide theſe three words for Vſury, I can finde not one Hebrew
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4377:18"/> word more, upon divers diligent ſearchings. Nor did others handling Vſury, ever name ſo many as I have, that I could finde, or heare of. As for <hi>N. T.</hi> it is expreſly named there, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely forbidden under the precept of free lending. And under all theſe names Vſury is made odious; therefore where is the name of that Vſury that Doctor <hi>Ames,</hi> or any, would intimate to be lawfull? 2 Reply to the clauſe is this: All Vſury in Scripture is either <hi>Neſhech,</hi> or <hi>Tharbith,</hi> or <hi>Terakim:</hi> But all theſe are vilified and diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Scripture as odious, therefore all Vſury in Scripture is forbidden, or diſgraced as unlawfull. The two firſt expreſly forbidden. The laſt word is, you ſee, not uſed in any precept or poſition about Vſury, but onely as a name of the wicked rich man, and you ſee what an odious ſignification it hath; inſomuch that the Vſurers conſcience ſhall judge whether <hi>Terakim</hi> is not ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in Scripture, when called cozening or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull dealing Vſury. For the Vſurer will not have his Vſury called cozening, or fraud, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. Nay, if they would but ſee how they are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and curſed for taking Vſe, they would diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Vſury. So <hi>Cic. Attic.</hi> 85.6. <hi>Primum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probantur hi quaeſtus, qui in odia hominum incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ut portitorum</hi> (toll or tax takers) <hi>&amp; foene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum.</hi> But alas Uſury in this is worſe than the worſt ſins. Thoſe deny the fact, but excuſe not the ſinne: Theſe confeſſe the fact but deny the ſinne. 2 Our reply to the laſt clauſe, that Vſury is taken away, <hi>quando debitum exigitur cum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4377:19"/> rigore, &amp;c.</hi> is briefly this. The breach of the Law, <hi>conſiſtit in indiviſibili.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be it never ſo ſmall, is ſinne. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>David</hi> ſmote him for cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment. It is laid to the charge of the old world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. that they brake the Law in the thoughts of their imaginations, and therefore God would bring upon them the flood. And, <hi>Curſed is he that continueth not in all the Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. But the Law takes hold of thoughts, <hi>Thou ſhall not covet,</hi> &amp;c. in the tenth Commandement. See how <hi>Paul</hi> applies it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. Therefore if all gaine forbare lending, for a bare principle, fully repayed, or to be repayed, be taken, be it more or leſſe, <hi>cum rigore,</hi> or <hi>abſque rigore,</hi> it is all the ſame. For how is it conceiveable that ſuch gaine ſhould be taken, <hi>ſine damno proximi,</hi> when the moſt Divines that preſſe reſtitution, doe it on this ground, Vſury ought to be reſtored, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath bin a damma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the ſo borrower. But ſaith Maſter <hi>Capel,</hi> The other part of the Schooles, with whom, ſaith he, I joyne, hold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, becauſe by Vſury there is no true title <hi>jure divino,</hi> no not in juſtice, to that which comes in that way. He quotes in the margent, <hi>Greg. de Valent. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>diſ.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 21. <hi>pu.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Scriptura tollit illam uſuram quae charitati repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> Luc. 6.35. <hi>i.e.</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cripture takes away the Vſury that is repugnant and oppoſite to charity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>Therefore the Scripture takes away all Vſury. 1 Becauſe all is oppoſite to charity. No man but would borrow freely if he could, therefore you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4377:19"/> ought ſo to lend. 2 Becauſe oppoſite to the Law of God as we heare, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5. reſtore the hundreth part, without mention of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is poore, or biting, &amp;c. But the ſumme of the Law is charity. As Chriſt approves the anſwer of the Lawyer. <hi>Ergo.</hi> 3 Becauſe oppoſite to that place, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35. alleaged by Doct. <hi>Ames, Lend freely, looking for nothing.</hi> Finally take notice, that whereas before the learned Doctor averred, that borrowing ought to be free could not be proved; yet here he alleageth this of <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Lend freely,</hi> which not to obſerve, is againſt the law of charity, ſaith the Doctor. Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſaith Maſter <hi>Smith,</hi> is againſt charity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forſan &amp; illam omnem Vſuram tollit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quae ex lege politica Iudaeis inter ſe exercere non licebat. Deut.</hi> 33.19, 20. Perhaps alſo it takes away all that Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which was not lawfull for the Jews, by the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Law, to exerciſe one towards another. Unto a ſtranger thou maiſt lend upon Uſury, but unto thy brother thou ſhalt not lend upon Uſury; that the Lord thy God may bleſſe thee in all thou ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy hand unto, &amp;c. <hi>Vnae Scriptura indicare videtur aliquam Vſuram eſſe per ſe licitam: Dum aequali, non egeno extraneo accipere Vſuras Iudaeis permittebat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great glory is made of this Text,<note place="margin">Replicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. in gener.</note> to prove Uſury not ſimply unlawfull. But as permiſſion by law to execute death upon malefactors, doth not prove murther not ſimply unlawfull: So to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of Vſury here towards them whoſe lives
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4377:20"/> the Jewes might take away, doth not prove but that Vſury is nevertheleſſe ſimply unlawfull. For al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ever gave a reaſon why Vſury towards the Canaanites (for the ſeven kingdomes of the Canaanites are the onely ſtrangers here meant, by the confeſſion of the learned, and no other ſtrangers) was permitted, was becauſe their lives were given to the Jewes, and conſequently their eſtates too. Therefore to object a private Jew might not take away a Canaanites life, is onely to argue, that a private Jew might not take Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a Canaanite. For the Canaanites goods is not his, except the life. Therefore this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (that is grounded on that which doth not appeare in the Text, that a private Jew might not kill a Canaanite) doth inferre theft to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to prove Vſury not unlawfull. For if a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Jew hath no power over the Canaanites life, then not over his eſtate; for what other rule is there? and ſo taking that he hath nothing to doe with, he robs. If he, a private Jew, takes uſe of him, ſurely if he doth it by vertue of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick politicall Law, dirived to him particularly; ſure then the reaſon or ground of that law being publick that Jewes are to have power over the Canaanites lives, comes downe to him in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: Or elſe his particular and private Vſury is without reaſon. 2 God tolerated the Jewes rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Egyptians: yet it doth not follow thence, that theft is not ſimply unlawfull <note n="q" place="margin">Therefore Maſter Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ins m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es this a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Law. That the Law is ſtill pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory, and ſtill the ſame in nature. The Law-makers diſpenſation being but for a ſpeciall &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular time or occaſion. And his act tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio in partic. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Suppoſe this were a toleration of Vſury for the Jew upon the Canaanite, without conſideration
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4377:20"/> of power over the Canaanites lives; yet what were this to uphold any kinde of Vſury to be uſed of and towards Chriſtians? when as two learned men, <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Willet,</hi> doe not doubt from this place (which ſeemes a toleration) to conclude Vſury to be utterly unlawfull among Chriſtians. Their argument is this. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes were forbidden to take any Vſury at all of their brethren; of the Gentiles they might; but now <hi>diruta eſt maceries,</hi> the wall of partition is taken away, there is neither Jew nor Gentile, but all are one in Chriſt: therefore Chriſtians may not take uſe of Chriſtians. Before this argument Maſter <hi>Willet</hi> puts this poſition [Vſury is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply unlawfull:] He makes the ſaid argument his firſt argument, and at the end of it he ſubſcribes <hi>Calvin.</hi> The ſecond particular Reply, From the manner of the Holy Ghoſts ſetting downe this rule touching Vſury, and mens urging, <hi>ſc.</hi> as a toleration. Vpon which, Maſter <hi>Capels</hi> poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this: <q>I know, ſaith he, the Law per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Vſury to the Jewes to the ſtranger. What of that? It followes the rather, that it is of it ſelfe a ſin; becauſe permiſſion is of ſins, not of duties.</q> So Maſter <hi>Capel.</hi> Meditate well on this anſwer. Perhaps at the firſt ſight you will wonder, and object, Doth God then tolerate ſin? Before he tolerated it is ſimply ſinne, and ſo it is when his toleration ceaſeth. But God being above the Commandement, his Will being the everlaſting platforme of the Commandement, he may diſpenſe; and when and how farre he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4377:21"/> makes it no Law, there is no tranſgreſſion. The morall Law was written, ſay the generall conſent of Divines, in <hi>Adams</hi> heart, and ſo was from the beginning, and yet ſtill is in force. Yet at firſt it was no adultery for the brother to marry the ſiſter: I meane no breach of the Commandement of Adultery: God ſhewing by neceſſity, his Will for that generation, to diſpence. So, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> is a Negative Commandement, and ſo binds <hi>ſemper,</hi> and <hi>ad ſemper.</hi> But when God bids the Iſraelites borrow of, and not pay the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, this is no theft: God having a reaſon, that the breach of this Commandement then was greater juſtice than to keepe it. The ſame may be ſaid for Vſury. If Kings and Emperours muſt be obeyed in their wholſome lawes, under penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſin: But it is no ſin to doe contrary to any law they make, when firſt they have for that time repealed them. Then God hath much more that power. The third particular reply is, That in the judgement of moſt learned men, the reaſon of this diſpenſation, <hi>viz.</hi> the leave the Jewes had to ſlay the Canaanites, doth the more ſhew the vileneſſe and cruelty of Vſury. Firſt, let us heare Maſter <hi>Capel,</hi> that we may knit this to that which was but quoted of him, that he may the better cleare himſelfe. The thing is (ſaith Maſter <hi>Capel</hi>) There was a Law to kill the Canaanite, and yet I hope that killing was not murther: No more was that Vſury a ſinne to them. Next, let us heare Maſter <hi>Willet,</hi> backing himſelfe with the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reaſons of the Fathers. if it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4377:21"/> (ſaith Maſter <hi>Willet</hi>) that God permitted the Hebrewes to take Vſury of the Gentiles, therefore it was not ſimply unlawfull. To this (ſaith he) it may be anſwered, that they were thoſe ſeven Nations of the Canaanites, of whom they might take Vſury: which Nations they were commanded to deſtroy, and ſo by this meanes they might weaken their eſtate, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſh them. Whereupon (ſaith Maſter <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let) Ambroſe</hi> inferreth, <hi>Ab hoc Vſuram exige, quem non ſit crimen occidere</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>And,</hi> cui jure inferuntur ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, huic legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma indicuntur Vſura.</note>. And ſo (ſaith he) <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> alſo concludeth, <hi>Non minus crudelis qui pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perem trucidat f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nore, quam qui eripit diviti.</hi> Adde to theſe <hi>Simler; Vbi jus belli, ibi jus Vſurae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si enim omnis Vſura eſſet intrinſecè ac ſuâ naturâ mala,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>tum non potuere Iudaei à gentibus accipere Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ſine ſcandalo gravi, quo gentes averterentur à religione ac lege Iudaeorum, quae admitteret rem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitam tanquam licitam. i.e.</hi> For if all Vſury in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecally, and in its owne nature were evill, then the Jewes could not have taken Vſury of the Gentiles, without great ſcandall, to the averting of the Gentiles from the religion and law of the Jewes tolerating a thing unlawfull.</p>
            <p>By the ſame reaſon we may ſay,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> If theft had beene intrinſecally, and in its owne nature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, then the Jewes could not have borrowed of the Egyptians jewels, not repaying them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great ſcandall, whereby the Egyptians might be turned away from the religion and Law of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4377:22"/> Jewes, which did admit of a thing, unlawfull in the opinion of the Egyptians, to be as lawfull. But we know that theft was ſimply, and in its owne nature unlawfull, notwithſtanding this diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So was Uſury, notwithſtanding that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this borrowing of jewels, as that lending upon Uſury, was an act of diſtributive ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to juſtly puniſh male factors, as enemies of the common ſtate of the Church, not belonging to commutative juſtice of trading and trafficking, borrowing, lending, &amp;c. 2 We are not to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Gods Lawes by the uncertaine rule of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall taken by graceleſſe men <note n="ſ" place="margin">For the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the liberty thereof was a ſcandall to the Iewes, &amp; fooliſhneſſe to the Gentiles, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note>, but rather by the holineſſe and uprightneſſe of Gods will, which we know to be ſo perfect, that the lawes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations it dictates, cannot be condemned of ſcandall-giving. 3 We know murther was ſimply unlawfull. And no doubt but the Canaanites would take great offence at Jew &amp; Jewiſh religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Jews invading their Kingdomes, would kill any of the Canaanites; yet neither of theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons made it unlawfull or inconvenient (God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them this liberty) to kill &amp; deſtroy all Jericho and Ay, &amp;c So, nor the law againſt theft, nor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that might be taken by the Gentile, made it unlawfull or inconvenient for the Jew to pick the Cannaanites pocket by Uſury, ſeeing they might doe more (by divine diſpenſation) <hi>viz.</hi> cut their throats, as an act of juſt war. The Kings law is ſtill current, that murther and robbing is felony and death; though he ſends his officer to take away the life and goods of one that is not to be owned
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4377:22"/> for a free Deniſon, but rather ſtanding under a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine power, denying the Kings Supremacy, as Jeſuites, &amp;c. So the Canaanites denied the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites to have any right to Canaan, or authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over them; and therefore the Jewes took their lives, or goods, or both, as forfeited, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the ſimple unlawfulneſſe of murther, theft, Uſury, &amp;c. 4 This toleration, in ſtead of taking offence, might probably bring in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites to turne to the Jewiſh Religion. For when they ſaw no Jewes life or goods in jeopardy by war and Uſury, but the Cananites, they might reaſon within themſelves who would be a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanite, and not a Jew? Seeing that which is ſimply <hi>illicitum,</hi> unlawfull among the Jewes and their confederates, is counted as a lawfull act and execution of common juſtice upon a Canaanite, to take away his goods by Uſury, nay, <hi>Neſhech,</hi> biting Uſury, and his life by warre. For ſo in <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. Of thy brother thou ſhalt not take <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Neſhech,</hi> but <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>extraneo, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Taſhich, foenerabis;</hi> which <hi>Taſhich</hi> is of the root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies to take <hi>Neſhech,</hi> biting Uſury: which Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> condemned as ſimply unlawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Huc etiam referri poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod maximè probabile ſit ex parabola illa de Talentis.</hi> Matth. 25.27. <hi>Non tantum in vulgari uſu fuiſſe apud Iudaeos menſario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aliquod foenus, ſed etiam à Domino non fuiſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatum, quia ſub illa ſimilitudine exigit officium ſpirituale ſine ulla infinuatione alicujus improbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, qualem in aliis parabolis, quae ab uſu improbato
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4377:23"/> officium illuſtrabant, ſolebat adhibere.</hi> Luc. 16.8. <hi>i. e.</hi> Thither may be referred that likely conjecture out of the Parable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27. <hi>viz.</hi> that not only there was a certaine Uſury among the Jewes, commonly uſed by the money-changers, but alſo that it was not diſallowed of the Lord; becauſe under that ſimilitude he requireth a ſpirituall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without any intimation of diſallowing it; which he was wont to expreſſe in other parables, illuſtrating a duty from or by ſome diſallowable act. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>As for the Parable of the Talents, I never heard any learned Divine, or any other Chriſtian urge it, but thoſe that are Uſurers, in the behalfe of Uſury. For if the Text be well weighed, the compariſon ſmites Uſury: For this compariſon was not uſed, but upon a ſpeciall occaſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion. The man of one Talent alleageth for his idleneſſe, the unreaſonableneſſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that he reaped where he ſowed not. Why then ſaith the Maſter, if thou hadſt thought ſo indeed, or if I had beene ſo indeed, thou ſhouldſt and wouldſt have runne upon unreaſonable wages of bringing in advantage to me, even to have put my money to Uſe, to give me content: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou didſt not doe ſo, it is evident that thou didſt not take me for a cruell Maſter, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſumedſt on my clemencie, and ſo didſt not by honeſt gaine peruſe my Talent, as all the reſt have done, and brought in advantage, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Uſury. For had our Saviour in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4377:23"/> connived at Uſury, he would as well have aggravated the ſluggiſhneſſe of this owner of one Talent, from the manner how they got their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe (if they had meddled with Uſury) as from the matter they had gained. To this effect <hi>Pareus</hi> Comments on the place; <hi>Abſcondiſti talentum, quia ſciebas me metere quod non ſeminavi. Imo, ſi ſciebas me talemeſſe; ſi vera eſſet tua criminatio, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondere non debuiſti, ſed elocare talentum, ut reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perem cum lucro. Sic falſam criminationem ipſius facto convincit, &amp; vanum ignavia praetextum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellit.</hi> So that to me it ſeemes evidently, that the Lord intimates that to be ſuch a one as to reape where another ſowes, is juſt to be as a Uſurer; and that there is no ſatisfying ſuch a Maſter, but by paying Uſe-money. Were this a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon the compariſon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.43, 44. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>De Domino, dieque illo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, ut fure noctu veniente, ita venturo, quod maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè probabile ſit, non tantum in vulgari uſu fuiſſe apud Iudaeos furtum, ſed etiam à Domino non fuiſſe impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum; quia ſub illa ſimilitudine exigit officium ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale (nempe vigilias ſpirituales) ſine ulla inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuatione alicujus improbationis, qualem in aliis para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolis quae ab uſu improbato officiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illuſtrabant, ſolebat adhibere.</hi> Luc. 16.8? No, I ſhould be cryed out againſt for ſuch a Gloſſe. Then may I diſlike the like Gloſſe upon the Parable of the Talents, like word for word. Others anſwer this place to the ſame effect, <hi>viz.</hi> This place (ſay they) will no more warrant lending on Uſury, than Chriſt his comparing his comming to judgement to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4377:24"/> ſudden comming of a thiefe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.43, 44. will warrant their ſuddenly breaking into mens houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Aequitas lucri demonſtrari poteſt, ex aequitate manifeſtâ, de qua nemo poteſt dubitare, ſi quis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum certum reditum vel ſummam ſibi praeciſe pendi ſtipuletur, ſed ita pecuniam ſuam apud probum virum collocet ut in illius fide acquieſcat. De hujuſmodi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniae collocatione nulla poteſt eſſe quaeſtio, ſi pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum capitalis maneat commune. Nihil enim eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud quam contractus ſocietatis in lucro &amp; damno. i. e.</hi> The equity of gaining, can be demonſtrated by a manifeſt equity doubted of by none; <hi>viz.</hi> If any one ſhall not bargain for any certaine returne, or ſumme of gaine to be preciſely paid unto him, but ſo putteth out his money to an honeſt man, that he reſts in his faithfulneſſe. Of this way of putting out of money there can be no queſtion, if the hazard of the Principle be common to them both; for its nothing but partnerſhip in gain &amp; loſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>Doth the Uſurer thus put out his money? No in no caſe: His conſcience and his ſecurity will witneſſe the ſame. What is all this then to prove the lawfulneſſe of putting to Uſe? No more than he that to prove a thing to be chalke, uſeth this argument, becauſe it is cheeſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Nihil contra aequitatem committitur ſi lucrum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certum, quod probabiliter ſequetur, vendatur pro certo moderato. i. e.</hi> There is nothing committed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to equity, if a gaine uncertaine, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4377:24"/> following, be ſold for a moderate gaine certaine.</p>
            <p>But what proofe is there of this? Not a word.<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> We therefore that are <hi>nullius addicti jurare in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba magiſtri,</hi> may juſt ſo anſwer the argument as it is propoſed, ſaying, it is <hi>contra aequitatem.</hi> And what is now won or loſt? But we will give a reaſon of what we ſay. If falſe ballances be abominable, to fell leſſe for money than one ought; If going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ones brother, and circumventing him, to ſell naughty commoditie for good, is unlawfull; then ſure it is unlawfull to ſell nothing for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; which a man doth often, when a man ſels <hi>lucrum incertum.</hi> So the Doctor confeſſeth. He ſaith, <hi>quod probabiliter ſequetur.</hi> We ſay that alſo, <hi>probabiliter non ſequetur.</hi> For ſo we ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in trading. So we finde by Scripture upon all men. All things come alike to all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Of riches in particular: They have wings. And of dealing ſo as to break the Commandements, it brings a curſe on all we put our hands to. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. And of this ſort is Uſury, <hi>ſc.</hi> unjuſt gaine. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.8. And it brings a curſe on all we put our hands to, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19, 20. Whiles therefore the Uſurer will ſell, and the borrower will buy Gods providence over his head, you ſee more likely in Uſury Gods curſe, and loſſes are bought and ſold over mens heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neque iniquitatis quicquid eſt in eo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſi contractus fiat legibus aequis, ut totum periculum capitalis perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat ad eum qui exercet pecuniam. Nihil enim aliud
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4377:25"/> eſt quam contractus aſſecurationis quo alienae rei pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum pretio aeſtimabile ſuſcipitur pro pretio. i. e.</hi> Neither is there any injuſtice in it, if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract be made with equall conditions, that the whole hazard of the principle lie upon him which uſeth the money, being nothing elſe but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of inſurance, whereby the hazard of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers goods valuable at a price, is undertaken for a price.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>Did not the Doctor but now ſay, <hi>De pecuniae collocatione nulla poteſt eſſe quaeſtio, ſi periculum capitalis maneat commune?</hi> Therefore it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>ſi non ſit commune, eſt quaeſtio</hi> — 2 How there may be <hi>contractus legibus aequis factus de re injuſtâ facienda,</hi> is beyond any man of ſound reaſon to conceive. 3 If it be <hi>rei alienae periculum,</hi> why ſhould it not ſo abide? why ſhould any man lend for care? why ſhould he lay another mans ſacks upon his ſhoulders? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing there is danger of ſinne to be laid on the borrowers ſhoulders, as well as care, to helpe the Vſurer to ſinne and live unprofitably, which could not be without the borrower. If it be <hi>rei alienae periculum,</hi> how ſhall it be on both ſides, that neither hath wrong, <hi>ſc. pretio aestimabile?</hi> It is all in Gods hands how great the <hi>periculum</hi> may be. One wedge may fire all the ſtuffe of <hi>Achan.</hi> By occaſion of this Vſury-money, the borrower may fall into dealing that may inwrap all his eſtate, and all may be loſt.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4377:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Non neceſſario requiritur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ut iſtiuſmodi contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus diſtincte aut expreſſe fiant, ſed ſatis eſt ſi fiant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitè ex intentione ſincerâ, &amp; ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aeſtimationem proborum. i.e.</hi> It is not neceſſary that ſuch like contracts be made diſtinctly and expreſly, it being ſufficient if they be made implicitly, out of a ſincere intention ratably by honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Its no need indeed that the contract be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe for the committing of the ſinne of Vſury.<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> For the Doctor ſaid before, <hi>Vſura eſt lucrum ex mutuo quaeſitum, non conventum; quia eſt Vſura tam mentalis, quam realis</hi> — 2 To ſeeke <hi>intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſinceram</hi> in an Vſurer, is to looke a roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong nettles, figs on thornes, and grapes of thiſtles. 3 For the <hi>aeſtimatio proborum,</hi> be bold of it, they will be judges of no ſuch matters, unleſſe they may judge the loſſe upon the idle unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vſurer, and the gaine to the labouring bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si iſti omnes contractus ſeparatim ſint liciti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus ex iis compoſitus ſit licitus. i.e.</hi> If all theſe contracts be ſeparately and ſingly lawfull, then one compounded of them is lawfull.</p>
            <p>To theſe ſeverally we have anſwered,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall reaſons and allegations: And therefore I wonder the worthy Doctor would once ſpeake ſuch a word <hi>[ut omnes concedunt.]</hi> Therefore of theſe <hi>lucra,</hi> ſingle or mixt, we conclude with the old verſe,
<q>
                  <l>Et quae non proſint ſingula, mixta mala.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:4377:26"/> Or with this,
<q>
                  <l>Singula ſi noceant, eadem quoque juncta nocebunt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaeſtio quarta eſt, quaenam obſervanda ſunt ad peccatum vitandum in pecuniâ exponenda?</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> The fourth queſtion is, what rules are to be obſerved, whereby to avoid ſinne in putting out money?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>It ſhould ſeeme there is a common fault and ſinne in putting out of money, by the Doctors confeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note>But he thinks it avoidable by theſe cautions: 1 <hi>Ne quid ultra ſortem exigatur ab egenis.</hi> 2 <hi>Ne lucri aviditas impediat foeneratorem quo minus pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres ſimpliciter donando juvet.</hi> 3 <hi>Non totum illud exigere, quod legibus &amp; uſu recepto licet. i.e.</hi> 1 That nothing above the principle be exacted of the poore. 2 That greedineſſe of gaine hinder not the Vſurer from lending to the poore. 3 That he exact not all that law and cuſtome tolerates.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>1 Let the Vſurers conſcience, and <hi>vox populi</hi> witneſſe, whether theſe cautions be obſerved. 2 If theſe be obſerved; yet God witneſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Vſurer. <hi>Non vitatur peccatum in pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia exponenda,</hi> as I have already cleared it out of Gods Word, canvaſed &amp; argued with the allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; reaſons of godly &amp; learned authors. 3 To make the queſtion, <hi>An Vſura ſit licita;</hi> and to put downe, dictate and ſuggeſt cautions, without
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4377:26"/> proofe, as ſufficient to take away the nature of Vſury, is <hi>petitio principii,</hi> a begging of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spectanda ſemper, &amp; obſervanda regula aquitatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; charitatis; ut illud tantum accipiatur, quod quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que bona fide vellet à ſe accipi in ſimili neceſsitate deprehenſo. i.e.</hi> Alwayes the rule of equity and charity is to be obſerved. <hi>viz.</hi> That ſo much on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be taken, which every one in very deed, would have to be taken of him, were he in the ſame condition.</p>
            <p>We have already ſhewed,<note place="margin">Replicatio.</note> that in committing this ſinne of Vſury more or leſſe, there can be no equity or charity found: For if there could, the queſtion were yeelded, Vſury were not ſinne. 2 For doing as one would be done by, <hi>i.e.</hi> ſay the Schoolmen, <hi>ſecundum rectam rationem. Saul</hi> would have his armour-bearer run him thorow; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might <hi>Saul</hi> runne his armour-bearer thorow? The lender upon Vſury thinks it no ſinne ſo to lend; therefore if he were in the borrowers caſe, he would not doubt but lawfully ſo to borrow. But if the Vſurer and the Borrower were well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>ſecundum rectam rationem,</hi> they would know (as very learned men hold) it is unlawfull to borrow or lend upon Vſe, and ſo would neither doe, nor be done to upon Vſury.</p>
            <p>The Caution.<note place="margin">D. <hi>Ames.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Offenſiones &amp; calumniae (quibus obnoxium eſt hoc genus co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ractuum.</hi> Jer. 15.10.) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinari ſemper dabeat, quantum fieri poteſt. i. e.</hi> The
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4377:27"/> laſt Caution is, that offences and calumnies (to which this kinde of contract is liable. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10.) ought to be avoided as much as may be.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Replicatio.</note>This daſheth neere all the Doctor hath laid down before in favour of Vſury. 1 He confeſſeth Vſury to be a thing of evill report, out of <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. 2 That offences muſt be avoided, &amp;c. we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre therefore Vſury muſt be left. 1 By the rule of this; <hi>Woe unto the world becauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. Better a milſtone,</hi> &amp;c. But ſo doe Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers offend many of their clients, to curſing. So doe they offend their Miniſter, to heart-breaking ſorrow, eſpecially at times of Communion. 2 By the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. <hi>Whatſoever is of good report,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If there be any praiſe, thinke of theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> farre of Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> urged at our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. There was another authour named, <hi>(ſed excidit memoriâ)</hi> whereby to countenance Vſury, as if the urging of mens authority without their reaſons, were of any validity.</p>
            <p n="1">1 We <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> could fill a ſheet of learned mens names, that hold againſt Vſury, if that were a confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I wiſh from my heart, that thoſe that are affected with the multitude of authours to ſway their Tenent, would read the Engliſh Vſurer, where they ſhall meet with a multitude of learned au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors condemning Vſury, and their ſound reaſons too; <hi>viz.</hi> 6 learned pious Biſhops; 10 learned pious Doctors; 22 learned pious Divines; with an addition of the witty reaſons of three famous
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4377:27"/> Engliſh Poets. 2 If we run upon mens authorities, we ſhall be robbed of all the Commandements, or the maine branches of them. The learned Atheiſt will take away the firſt Commandement.<note place="margin">I have ſeene in Cardinall B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onius his Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud the ſecond Com. bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tted out with his own pen, And left out in Rom. Catech. Concil. Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſ. Concil. Ta rocon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſ. c. 3. Concil. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terancoſ. par. 16. c. 1. See alſo Willet on Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 22. qu. 46.</note> The Papiſt the ſecond. The Anabaptiſt the third. The Jew the fourth. The Popes diſpenſations the fifth, ſixth, &amp; ſeventh. The Vſurer the eighth. The equivocating Jeſuite the ninth. The Papiſt the tenth, that Concupiſcence is no ſinne. 3 The Canoniſts and Canon Law have this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able decree; SI QUIS AFFIRMARE PRAESUMAT, EXERCERE USURAS NON ESSE PECCATUM, &amp;c. If any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to affirme that it is no ſinne to practiſe Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we decree him worthy to be puniſhed as an Hereticke. Finally, we have not onely learned pious mens arguments in abundance to prove Vſury unlawfull, but that it is ſo unlawfull, as that reſtitution muſt be made; Vſurers being bound to it by the Law of God. See <hi>Capel</hi> of Temptations; That it is utterly unlawfull to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row upon Vſe. So the learned Jewes and Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines. See <hi>Ainſworth</hi> on <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. They prove it out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhall not cauſe to bite; Thou ſhalt not cauſe to lend upon biting Vſury.</hi> By traditon we have beene taught, that this is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to the borrower. Three times more in the ſaid place they ſay it is unlawfull to borrow upon Vſe. I adde, If Vſury be ſimply a ſinne, as the learned prove, and you have heard them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged: Then how can a man be acceſſary to it, and not be guilty?</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4377:28"/>
            <p>Finally, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> at our Conference (as I remember) there was urging of neceſſity in ſome caſes, to take and give upon Vſe; and it is common to men to make thouſands of caſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>But if God (on paine of excluding heaven) forbids Vſury, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. ſure no caſe can make it neceſſary. <hi>Capel</hi> to this alleageth <hi>Tullie,</hi> That no neceſſity can licence a man to take that which is not ones owne. And <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> that theſe in caſe of neceſſity, is ſtill ſin. Nor may we, nor can we upon any pretence conceive, that God will ſo prevent mans good, that he will make it condemnation to doe that, which our Caſes (we make) ſay we muſt needs doe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
